Upload video, watch video. Sounds
simple. YouTube processes 500 hours of
video every minute. That's 30,000 hours
of content uploaded every hour. The
engineering behind this interface is
complex. Let's design YouTube. Not the
billion user version, but a smaller
system that we can learn from. This
video covers the core components. We'll
focus on video upload and streaming.
There's much more to YouTube. search,
recommendations, comments, monetization.
Each could be its own deep dive. Today,
we'll build a foundation you can extend.
Here are the requirements we'll focus
on. People upload massive videos. A
10-minute 4K video ranges from 1.5 GB
highly compressed to 30 GB in ProRes.
When uploading huge videos, users expect
resumable uploads. For viewing, playback
must adapt to network condition in real
time. When your connection drops from 25
megabit per second to 2 megabit per
second, playback shouldn't stop. The
upload challenge reveals the first
design decision. We could route large
videos through our API servers,
configure streaming instead of
buffering, increase time out from 30
seconds to 30 minutes, handle partial
uploads is all solvable. But why make
our servers handle gigabytes of pass
through traffic when they could be
serving actual API requests? There's a
better pattern. use pre-signed URLs. Our
API server generates a temporary signed
URL that grants direct upload permission
to blob storage. The client uploads
straight to storage. Our server stay
free to handle other work. Blob storage
gives us another benefit. We get
multiport uploads built in. The client
splits the videos into chunks. Each
chunk is 5 to 10 megabyte. It's small
enough to upload quickly on slower
connections. Large enough to minimize
overhead. Each chunk get a SH 256
fingerprint. The client uploads chunks
in parallel. Six chunks uploading
simultaneously is common. This pattern
appears in Dropbox, Google Drive, and
backup services. Any system handling
large files uses similar approaches.
The processing pipeline presents a
different challenge. Video transcoding
burns massive compute cycles. User
uploads videos in many different
formats. iPhone record in HGVC. Android
phones uses H.264.
Someone uploads a 4K Pro file from Final
Cut Pro. We need these videos playable
on every device. Old Android phones run
ancient Android. Smart TVs from 2018,
web browsers that haven't updated in
years. The solution is a processing
pipeline that converts one video into
many versions. We generate multiple
resolutions from 2160p down to 240p. We
need so many because network conditions
and device speeds vary widely. Someone
on fiber with a fast device needs 4K.
Someone on 3G with an ancient phone
needs 240p. Then consider codecs. H264
works everywhere but uses more
bandwidth. VP9 saves bandwidth but older
devices can decode it. AV1 saves even
more bandwidth but needs powerful
hardware. We encode in all three. Next,
we package these in containers. MP4 for
maximum compatibility. Webb for web
optimization. Now one upload becomes 15
to 20 files. How do we process
efficiently? Model the workflow as a
DAG. DAG stands for the directed as
cyclic graph. Each processing step is a
note. Dependencies are edges. The
asyclic part matters. It ensures task
can complete without circular
dependencies. First split the video into
segments. Videos have key frames every
two to 10 seconds. These frames send
alone without referencing others. Split
a key frames now use segment processes
independently. The workflow splits into
multiple streams. Video, audio, and
metadata each take their own path
through the system. Video segments fan
out to hundreds of workers while one
machine transcodes segment one to 1080p.
Another handles segment 2 to 720p. Audio
processing runs in parallel on different
hardware. Thumbnail generation and
subtitle extraction happen on their own
dedicated workers. This is the power of
modeling work as a DAG. One video
becomes hundreds of parallel tasks
across a worker farm. As each task
completes, results flows to the next
stage. Sequential processing would take
hours. Parallel processing completes in
minutes. Now streaming. Modern video
streaming uses adaptive bitray
streaming. The video player doesn't
download one file. It downloads
segments, small chunks of videos, each a
few seconds long. When network bandwidth
is high, the player fetches 1080p
segment. When bandwidth drops, it
switches to 480p segments. The
transition is usually seamless. This
work through manifest files. The primary
manifest lists all available formats.
Each format then has its own media
manifest with URLs for every segment.
The player reads manifests, monitors
bandwidth using the download speed of
the recent segments, and fetches the
probate segments. All this happened
invisibly. The player makes HTTP range
requests. Give me 1,000 to 2,000 of
segment five of the 720p version. This
enables instance seeking to jump to
minute 47. The player calculates which
segments to fetch. These segments are
stores in CDN's, content delivery
networks. Popular videos cache across
edge servers worldwide. A viewer in
Tokyo get segments from Tokyo, not
California. Geographic proximity means
lower latency, better streaming. We've
just scratched the surface. Several
areas deserve deeper exploration. The
hot video problems challenges every
video platform. When one video goes
viral, millions request it
simultaneously. We need metadata caching
and database hotspot prevention. Cost
optimization requires trade-offs. Do we
transcode everything immediately or
popular formats first? Should rare
formats use ondemand transcoding? When
do we migrate to code storage? Pipeline
optimization can improve latency. Stop
processing segments as they arrive
instead of waiting for complete upload.
Pipeline to upload and processing for
faster availability. We could explore
geographic CDN placement, readwrite
ratios or lazy transcoding strategies.
Each topic could be its own deep dive,
but the fundamentals remain the same.
What makes this design work at scale?
Direct uploads keep servers free for
actual logic. DAX transforms sequential
bottlenecks into parallel workflow.
Adaptive streaming ensures smooth
playback regardless of network
conditions. Once we understand these
principles, we see them everywhere.
Large file sharing, machine learning
pipelines, and live streaming all build
on these same foundations.
Ready to ace your next technical
interview? Join our community where we
offer comprehensive courses on system
design, coding, behavioral questions,
machine learning, and object-oriented
design. Learn more at bitebico.com.